Tell your daughters of this year,
与您女儿谈谈，在过去的一年。
how we woke needing coffee
我们是如何依赖咖啡苏醒，
but discovered instead cadavers strewn about our morning papers,
却发现尸体在晨报上看到，
waterlogged facsimiles of our sisters, spouses, small children.
悲剧同样也来自于我们的姐妹、伴侣和年少的孩子。
Say to your baby of this year when she asks, as she certainly should,
当她问起，你要告诉她这一年发生了什么，她当然应该问
tell her it was too late coming.
告诉她，这一切来的太晚了。
Admit even in the year we leased freedom, we didn't own it outright.
承认吧，即使在我们获得自由的日子里，却没能全部地拥有。
There were still laws for every way we used our privates
我们的个人生活的林林总总被法律所桎梏
while they pawed at the soft folds of us,
他们抚弄我们柔软的褶皱
grabbed with no concern for consent,
违背我们的意愿去抓弄
no laws made for the men that enforced them.
与此同时，对于男性却没有同样的规则
We were trained to dodge,
我们被迫学会了躲避，
to wait, to cower and cover,
等待、退缩、掩饰，
to wait more, still, wait.
以及无尽地等待
We were told to be silent.
我们被要求保持沉默。
But speak to your girls of this wartime,
但是，跟你女儿讲讲这战争时期，
a year preceded by a score of the same,
和往昔无异的一年
so as in two decades before,
也和二十年前无异的一年
we wiped our eyes,
我们拭去泪水，
laced caskets with flags,
在棺材上铺好旗帜
evacuated the crime scene of the club,
疏散犯罪现场
caterwauled in the street,
在街道上疾呼
laid our bodies on the concrete against the outlines of our fallen,
躺在水泥地上，紧挨着我们倒下的身影，
cried, "Of course we mattered,"
哭喊着，“我们女性当然很重要，”
chanted for our disappeared.
为我们所失去的吟唱。
The women wept this year.
今年女性又在哭泣
They did.
哭泣
In the same year, we were ready.
同在这一年，我们也做好了准备
The year we lost our inhibition and moved with courageous abandon
我们失去了家园，带着勇气的流放去前进
was also the year we stared down barrels,
同时，我们对阻碍怒目而视
sang of cranes in skies, ducked and parried,
歌颂高飞的鹤群回避并闪躲着
caught gold in hijab, collected death threats,
火中取栗，视死如归
knew ourselves as patriots,
我们知道自己是爱国者，
said, "We're 35 now, time we settled down and found a running mate,"
说，“我们三十五岁了，是时候静下心来，寻找伴侣，”
made road maps for infant joy, shamed nothing but fear,
追求天伦之乐，问心无愧但仍心有所惧
called ourselves fat and meant, of course,
我们称自己身材肥硕，不过当然，是指
impeccable.
完美无瑕
This year, we were women,
这一年，我们是女人，
not brides or trinkets,
而非新娘或是饰品，
not an off-brand gender,
不是粗陋的性别，
not a concession, but women.
不是一味让步，而是女人。
Instruct your babies.
指引你的孩子。
Remind them that the year has passed to be docile or small.
提醒他们，被驯化和轻视的年代已经过去。
Some of us said for the first time that we were women,
有些人说，这是我们第一次身为女人
took this oath of solidarity seriously.
严肃对待这个团结的誓言。
Some of us bore children and some of us did not,
我们中的一些人养育了儿女，一些没有，
and none of us questioned whether that made us real
却无人问及这是否是让我们真实
or appropriate or true.
亦或是得体，或者正确
When she asks you of this year,
当她问及你这一年，
your daughter, whether your offspring or heir to your triumph,
您的女儿，无论是您的子嗣或者接班人，
from her comforted side of history teetering towards woman,
从她对女性历史理解的角度上，
she will wonder and ask voraciously,
她会疑惑并且迫切地发问
though she cannot fathom your sacrifice,
尽管她难以理解您的牺牲
she will hold your estimation of it holy,
她会对您敬重有加
curiously probing, "Where were you?
好奇的问，“您那时在身在何处？
Did you fight? Were you fearful or fearsome?
您抗争了嘛？您是否感到畏惧或令人闻风丧胆？
What colored the walls of your regret?
您的悔恨之墙是什么颜色？
What did you do for women in the year it was time?
那一年你为女性做了什么？
This path you made for me, which bones had to break?
您粉碎了何人之骨为我铺就道路？
Did you do enough, and are you OK, momma?
您是否尽力了？您还好吗？妈妈？
And are you a hero?"
您是个英雄吗？“
She will ask the difficult questions.
她会问及一些艰深的问题。
She will not care about the arc of your brow,
她不会在乎你眉毛的弧度，
the weight of your clutch.
你的离合器的重量
She will not ask of your mentions.
她不会问及你的顾虑。
Your daughter, for whom you have already carried so much, wants to know
你养育已久的女儿想要知道，
what you brought, what gift, what light did you keep from extinction?
你为避免毁灭而带来了什么，什么礼物与何种光？
When they came for victims in the night,
当灾难降临于受害者之夜，
did you sleep through it or were you roused?
你是否就这样睡去还是被唤醒？
What was the cost of staying woke?
保持清醒要付出何种代价？
What, in the year we said time's up, what did you do with your privilege?
在我们所说的一年将近之时，你用你手中的权力做了什么？
Did you sup on others' squalor?
你是否向邪恶妥协？
Did you look away or directly into the flame?
你的目光是否避开了熊熊烈火？
Did you know your skill or treat it like a liability?
你是否了解了你的能力并将其视为责任？
Were you fooled by the epithets of "nasty" or "less than"?
你是否被”讨厌“或者”不足“的偏见愚弄？
Did you teach with an open heart or a clenched fist?
你是否用了开放之心或者是紧握之拳进行教导？
Where were you?
你身在何处？
Tell her the truth. Make it your life.
告诉她真相。使它成为你生命中的一部分。
Confirm it. Say, "Daughter, I stood there
确认它。说，”女儿，我站在那里，
with the moment drawn on my face like a dagger,
在像刀锋一样划过我面庞的时刻，
and flung it back at itself,
把它掷回，
slicing space for you."
为你开辟了空间。“
Tell her the truth, how you lived in spite of crooked odds.
告诉她真相，你怎样是如何生存而不去管那些不诚实的怪人们
Tell her you were brave,
告诉她你曾勇敢，
and always, always in the company of courage,
永远，永远勇气与你相伴，
mostly the days when you just had yourself.
大多数日子里，当你独自一人。
Tell her she was born as you were,
告诉她，她的出生像你一样，
as your mothers before, and the sisters beside them,
如同之前你母亲，和她身边的姐妹们，
in the age of legends, like always.
都是在一个传奇年代。
Tell her she was born just in time,
告诉她，她生恰逢时，
just in time
正好来得及
to lead.
去引领。
(Applause)
（掌声）